the today I will talk about more for the
alignment the the the the problems in
speech
recogition um so last time last lecture
I we discussed about feature extraction
mainly even whether it is end to endend
or it is hmm based approaches uh we are
still using the L filter Bank a feature
as a kind of a very
efficient input and so on but that's
mostly for the input right and actually
during the the uh the uh lecture we also
had a questions about you know is that
the for the the the the text the output
or is that for the pH output the kind
of the final Target and so on and
actually we didn't talk so much about
the definition of the output over
problems so first I want to introduce
what could be the possible output that
we will handle uh in this spe con uh uh
the we basically uh shallowly kind of
mention this part but just want to
clarify this the first couple of minutes
so uh of course our goal is almost
always the
text for the case that if we want to
kind of analyze the our kind of the form
patterns and so on for some uh medical
analysis and so on uh the the uh
intermediate representation like a phone
and so on can be a kind of output of the
target but the majority of the speech
the recognition uh the target is to uh
get the text so that we are basically
that focusing on the text and however uh
the even text we actually have a couple
of
representations uh like for example the
we hover basically using the three types
of the uh the representation for the C
for the output TT one is
world uh this uh would be probably most
kind of familiar uh for people working
on the English the speech condition uh
that is quite kind of a the good unit it
has a kind of a also has a semantic
information synthetic information uh and
so on uh but the issue is that it tend
to be very large the the vocabulary size
could be the our natural kind of a
conversation uh vocabulary SI to be
30,000 or 40,000 but depending on the
our kind of a uh the the the scope of
you know try to kind
of understand everything the of course
the vocabulary side becomes the super
huge also uh B means that there are lot
of issues when we have out of vocabulary
so the this kind of out vocabulary issue
is also uh the cannot ignore as we have
in the the weekly assignment we often
have a lot of kind of new words or kind
of named entity and so on which is are
often not included in our predefined the
vocabulary so uh this uh the vocabulary
issues are are one more the is the the
the the drawback of the world based
approaches and the second approach is
character so this actually is the
exactly kind of opposite uh the
characteristics so first character uh is
quite small in terms of the number of
the the vocabulary size right uh like
for example in the English cases it
depend on which kind of character we
should include like a special character
and so on but generally around 30
including the Roman alphabet and so on
so this the size is not large in general
but it's depend on the languages again
uh like for example uh the
Chinese I think the order of the
character in The General use would be
the 30,000 so sorry th000 3,000 or
something like that right but the other
entire character set that it would have
10,000 or something yeah uh same for the
Japanese and depending on the language
some language actually has a large
character but still compared with the
the vocabulary of the vocabulary size of
the world it is hand the that we can
handle it and also that we not basically
have uh the out of vocabulary issues
almost all the kind of characters are
included in the our
pre-existing the the the dictionary
right we would not have so much cases
that we can create a new
characters except for probably Emoji now
Emoji will become quite popular and it's
May kind of a we may need to augment the
the character vocabulary with Emoji but
Emoji usually do not have a
corresponding sound so for speech cases
probably we don't have to include them
um however uh the it's actually has
similar the uh pros and cons that are
compared with world so for example go to
is represented by only two words right
the Lang two but if we uh the the use
the character uh to represent this one
uh the G d o and the the space and the T
it becomes the five character five
lengths right and generally the
character uh representation makes the
kind of a the length
longer length longer means that we need
to
actually H more
computations so it character is good in
terms of the vocabulary size issue but
computationally it could be very
expensive
and then the people actually using the
uh something between so this is the
called bite player encoding or sentence
piece uh generally we just kind of Marge
uh some of the character set and then
making it as a
subw but we still by the way keeping the
original uh the the character as well so
that the all kind of any of the text can
also be represented by this kind of a
set so it's including the character so
the similar to the character cases we
don't have a out of vocabulary issues
and since some of the word is some of
the word or some of the subw is still
kind of concatenated so actually the
sentence length is again something
between so that the we can have avoid
the issue of the very long computation
and a very large computation due to Long
other character so the basically that we
in this lecture we use these three types
of the character by the way the how to
which charact which kind of a uh the
the uh the unit we should use uh highly
depending on the language or highly
depending on the other data and so on
also computational cost and so on so
mostly people actually using that this
are the subw which is true but actually
for the CH Chinese ja jaanese cases many
people actually just using the
character and the word is very useful
for the case of the hmm because word
usually have a corresponding the
pronunciation and then that we can
connect it with the the the form based
system and so on so again uh this is
quite kind of a different depending on
other kind of a cases so I usually don't
specify this other which one I am
using except for the case for the HM
based approaches ver end but anyway
basically I didn't specify this one but
which means it can be any of them and if
you guys ask the question about in this
case which one we should use I'm happy
to answer but it's again depending on
the language or depending on training
data depending on the the demand of the
computational cost it is changing so
it's actually one of the the parameter
uh the hyper parameter in uh if we kind
of build a speech
system and this is uh the more for the
the final output but we also have a
several other intermediate
output so this is
phon and the phon is that already
explained a lot in
the week before so I didn't go through
so much but f is the first the the the
more acostic information and it's
required the dictionary to convert from
the world but after uh we have a kind of
a the uh the dictionary to convert the
hor this problem becomes kind of
shortcut right from webform to the text
sequence is very kind of a long in terms
of the how to kind of change it but the
this other pum is a kind of quite a nice
shortcut quite nice way to modularize
the problem uh the with the kind of
acoustic side and lugage side so the pH
still are widely used in hm based system
and so on and then that we also have
additional the information which is we
call it the state that is the more for
the the internal representation more the
more resolutionary information than for
but of course it doesn't mathematically
it's mathematically exist but it
doesn't observable so it is just a model
but we often also using the the state
well I will later introduce this other
the H Mar of model state but this is
more kind of a the fine the resolution
than the the the F the acoustic part and
this the representation is the O use in
the hmm base system so I just want to
recap that we have a world character
the B Band
coding or P or state this kind of
various kind of the output
representation uh we are handling so
that's a kind of remark of the
output uh any questions about the
output
unit okay so cool and then today uh I
will explain about alignment this is
also very important concept
so the first uh I will discuss about the
easy cases end2 Sr is actually easy in
terms of the explaining the what it is
although the realizing it with the neur
network is very complicated but the
basically the N2 and ASR is easy so I
will start to explain from the this one
so N2 and ASR is the direct mapping from
the observation uh the the feature to
the speech feature to the text
and without any kind of other
intermediate
representation like other pH based
approaches and then uh it has a three
kind of main architecture attention
based the connectionist temporal
classification CTC and Rec network uh
transducer uh and so on and today the
including hmm I will try to revisit this
kind of a method uh based on the kind of
alignment purpose alignment
perspective so first the attention based
ASR is actually the starting uh from the
same uh point to the PW
given so remember that that when we kind
of starting speech processing
formulation in the third weeks we always
kind of discuss about you know how to
kind of obtain this other the
probability uh and so on and the uh the
important issue is that the text or the
part it can be word or character or subw
but anyway this the W and observation
the language is
different so we are not sure are the
which one corresponding to which the the
the spech speech feature corresponding
to text and so on in general so the
problem is actually not just kind of
recognizing the speech but actually we
want to also find some kind of good data
assign
alignment problem and then the how
attention based approach is the doing is
as follows first we actually the
factorize PW given o based on the
probabilistic Chain
rule so because this W is still very
kind of a difficult to deal with because
it is sequence so instead of kind of
handling the entire sequence we are the
factorize this the problem as a kind of
the product of the
each word or each token uh they they and
then they the the converting the problem
to this the problem that is kind of the
most the uh important
factorization of the attention based the
As and then the uh the after we have a
probabilistic chain L to factorize this
kind of a
probability uh we actually have to uh
the the providing the actual neural
network uh for this uh
function and then uh we of use the
attention based method to align the
input and output and this one is called
Soft alignment so please are remember it
by the way we will have a more deep
other discussions about about attention
based ASR so in this lecture I just want
to more focus on the alignment
perspective and then other explain about
the each of the kind of method so if you
have more questions about attention
based ASL that you guys can ask that the
when I will explain it in the uh uh the
later
lecture okay so I will try to explain
the alignment problems
so first uh this is a kind of other the
MCC feature actually and then this is
corresponding to the the one two three
four five six seven only eight Dimension
but it's if you know make it 40 and so
it's too much so I only kind of
extrating eight but please consider that
this is the kind of after the mscc
feature extraction we have a this kind
of the sequence of the audio so t 1 2 3
4 5 two I think this is totally 32 or
something like that the first people
understand it this is just the speech
feature from one to 32 corresponding to
this kind of MSC
figure sorry 35 yeah and then uh the uh
this is actually the the word
c and word c are the let's say this Cas
is which just using a character as a
unit and in this case it's actually the
length is three right s
e so the problem here
is how to find the that this s are
corresponding to uh each of the
feature this e correspond to the the the
F features and the last e corresponding
to F feature
so this is a kind of a alignment
problem uh if people that understand it
it is clear okay good good yeah it's
some of you it's a very trivial but it's
very important concept so I kind of want
to spend
time and then what attention based
approach is doing is
that actually they try to find the
probability of uh this character the
belongs
to which feature so let's say this one
is a kind of a
probability how many percent this s can
be possibly aligned and then in this
cases three or four has a kind of a
higher probability than all the others
this means that it's most likely this s
will be kind of aligned here this three
and four
and then this can be very low
probability but it can be because it is
soft so that's why people call this kind
of approach soft
alignment uh same for the E uh let's say
for example this Cas is there are little
bit more kind of higher probability in
many of the other kind of frames so the
approximately five to let's say 20 is
have a higher probility this means that
the most likely this second e would be
kind of a align aligned with uh this
range of the
feature and
then the last one may also have a
similar pattern but have a more kind of
a the the probability in the last part
uh than the previous features uh and so
on
so uh this uh the is a one way to uh
represent the alignment right so again
each kind of a character or each kind of
a unit of the
output uh we try to get the probability
of uh that which one would have aligned
to the uh the the feature with some kind
of the probability so this uh it's
actually computed in attention based
approaches with that we can actually
compute the uh the correspondence of the
the
S and the E and other e uh and so
on so again the this is not
deterministic right this can be 20 or 21
or 22 even you know one two is not the
zero probability almost zero but it's
not zero completely zero and in the most
of the cases so again this kind of a
soft uh that uh the the softly kind of
aligning each of the character uh uh
that's uh we call it the soft uh
alignment so this is actually the the uh
the alignment method that the attention
based approach this cannot be same that
this distribution uh and it can be kind
of a the
following uh the the that e can be a
littleit bit earlier and the second e
can be little bit later
however uh uh the this is because it is
kind of a the the uh the we have a order
s so it can be actually the later but I
see your point actually this can be you
know just a kind of a e and long Bo
and so on so it can be actually the as
AUM representation it just kind of can
be regarded as a one long boil and may
not have to have this kind of
Distinction and so on but it's just kind
of since it is the this kind of order
and then the attention is trained to see
the kind of alignment and so on so it is
not actually actually we computed but
it's I just kind of virtually do it but
as a computational result probably it
would have this kind of pattern because
we have a order in the kind of the the
character side and then the
corresponding the the out input should
also have a order and so on however this
is a very important part so maybe I can
have a more kind of discussion in the
attention when I kind of explain but
maybe I can also mention it right now
this is that we the kind of tring data
uh we have this kind of P but one of the
issue of the attention based approach is
that this kind of a uh the the uh logic
is
not uh the the represented as a kind of
constant in the mathematical form so
this means that again even s can
actually be other
the the uh the even s can be the the the
H some probability here
but this should not happen right in
speech uh speech recognition is you know
almost kind of this kind of a the
representation is kind of a keeping the
order we call this kind of a property
monotonic alignment
property so so again you know it is very
kind of obvious that the S should not
have a probability here but attention
based approaches itself doesn't have
such kind of a hard the constraint and
generally putting some kind of small
other probability and so on so this
other nature is actually not very good
for speech other recognition but in the
other application like a machine
translation and so on since the order
can be different in the input and output
so for them actually this is a very good
property but for speech other
recognition cases since input and output
should be monotonic so that this kind of
a the property is not very desired
property okay so that's a very good
question and then actually the this are
connect to the next kind of other other
method C CTC and RN transer cases and
it's actually the based on the very
different uh the attention uh sorry the
alignment the pattern than the the
previous are the the uh the attention
based approaches so first the CTC is RN
transer or everything in the speech
condition always starting from PW given
all and again we s mentioned that W and
O is a different range so we need to
find some kind of a are the the
correspondence right and then the
previously attention based approaches is
more like kind of a soft alignment to S
of this other other issue but now CTC
RNN or even later hmm also actually
based on this kind of approaches we uh
actually have another solution for this
the correspondence it's called A Hard
alignment pass and this is actually more
intuitive so I can explain about
it so again that let's start about this
kind of problem input the speech feature
35 frames and the token this cases
character three and then last that in
the previous cases we just tried to kind
of get kind of the probability of the
each
assignment however in the hard alignment
cases we
actually hardly
assign uh like first one to six cases
each align to S and seven to the I think
around 20 each second e and the third
one uh would be the the list uh and so
on I think this is more intuitive for
you guys right however how to decide
this kind of a boundary is actually not
trivial or even it is not kind of
observable in many cases so instead of
kind of just consider one H case of the
alignment we actually are consider all
possible alignment so in this cases for
example uh this is one realization of
the alignment and the next one is little
bit shifted the E is kind of little bit
shift shifted so that's uh the the uh
the uh the pattern it also be possibly
happens so we actually consider all
possible this kind of the the
alignment uh that is kind of a hard
alignment cases the first hard alignment
is two kind of
uh making explicit hard kind of a the
the alignment property by the way for
this kind of a hard alignment process we
can actually set the monotonic alignment
property so we can that in addition to
this kind of a r the the hard alignment
we can also set the rule that this once
it is happened here uh this the S
doesn't go to kind of Be Active here uh
and so on hard alignment can
actually set this kind of constraint
easily and so on so this is actually
another difference with the soft the
alignment and so on but anyway the the
hard alignment is considering the kind
of a various uh the uh the the alignment
considerations and then find the kind of
the best ways or even kind of consider
everything and the uh the in the kind of
probabilistic manner that is a kind of a
hard alignment and so
on okay so it sounds like it's a kind of
way to for us to kind of represent this
kind of representation right and how to
kind of uh but this one is observation
this one is kind of the the token uh and
how to kind of represent this uh the
alignment hard alignment information
mathematically uh that is a kind of one
question and then
uh we actually can uh the the represent
uh introduce additional variable called
alignment variable it can be by the way
changed depending on the kind of a model
context in the kind of a the CTC or RN
transer cases I may call it alignment
variable but in the hmm based cases I
may also call it hmm variable and state
variable and so on it's depending on the
model the the this kind of variable can
be called differently I try to unify it
but if if not please understand that I
am talking about same thing but anyway
how to represent this kind of alignment
pattern mathematically for example this
cases from one to four is actually s and
five
to 9 is e right and then we have a kind
of this the kind of a the varable we
prepare D1 corresponding to S D2
corresponding to S D3 corresponding to S
Z4 corresponding to S D5 corresponding
to e and then we can actually represent
this kind of alignment but right by
introducing this variable and the same
if you know slightly this alignment is
changed this part is changed right
recognize yeah from here to here and
then we can also sely uh the present it
with the now the different the alignment
information in this case from the seven
it becomes e but from one to six it
becomes s right so by introducing this
kind of alignment variable we can
actually represent this the the pattern
and this pattern uh mathematically so
this is actually the hard
AR called the alignment variable here
here and which we will introduce for the
formulation so this the
alignment uh variable is actually
introduced uh newly uh for our kind of a
formulation and then CTC and RN
transducer is actually uh the uh the the
the formulated by the way the I I don't
do the uh questions anymore but if we
have a new such kind of a variable uh to
incorporate it to the kind of our PW
given law we use a sum rule okay please
also remember that if we have some kind
of try to introduce some kind of new
variables uh how to mathematically do it
we just using the sum Rule and then we
can actually uh incorporate the new
variable right and then the later how to
cook it is a different problem but at
least for the newly introducing some the
parameters Su rule is a kind of way to
do
that and then CTC is actually having
more equations and then finally kind of
uh the uh the breakdown to the the some
kind of probability which I will not
fully kind of explain it right now but
in the kind of a later stage I will
explain about the the CTC uh and this
more kind of the mathematical form of
how to derive this
equations and so on but the important
part is that the if we introduce this
D and then if this kind of D is given
this means that if we have this kind of
information uh the alignment information
is
given at least Z and the observation is
the same
RS so if if we the same RS it is in
correspondence right we have a
correspondence so we could use any of
the the technique any of the neural
network or whatever we don't need to use
attention and so on anymore so this is
actually how CTC is build after this
introduction of the D and then we
actually can make a kind of any of the
neural network to uh that the makers the
the speech recognition and so
on okay so this is for the end2 and ASR
cases what's happened in the hmm based
at the speech condition cases I will
also go through this part but generally
hmm based part is actually having a more
equation more mass because it's actually
try to kind of make the problem to be
tractable by using a lot of kind of the
assumptions and so on so for example
this one is already I kind of explained
but since this kind of equation is very
important so I want to kind of review it
again so first part uh we just the
introduce the uh the The Forum
representation Forum sequence and then
the sum rule to introduce this one right
and then we using the product rule to
factorize each of the kind of function
and then other we have a very good
questions you know the the the
Performing the conditional Independence
ass
here but is it really valid it's not
very valid but it's a kind of okay
assumption so we all can use it
otherwise this problem and this problem
is equivalent and there is no kind of uh
the the no kind of change in terms of
the difficulty but after the conditional
Independence assumption it becomes other
easier so this kind of way is the
factorization uh introduction of the new
variable based on the sum rule
factorization based on the product rule
and then simplifying some of the
dependency based on the conditional
Independence assumption this is what we
usually use for our problems and then
the again it becomes the uh the the
acostic modeling part part and language
modeling part that I can we already had
explained but uh the now that I will
talk about more for the hmm part which
is actually corres responding to the
this the acoustic modeling part and then
I will basically try to provide how this
alignment concept is applied to the hmm
cases and so
on so uh the uh hmm the cases uh the
problem is that
simil is actually again we have the
speech features
all but the pre previously uh in the end
to end cases we actually deal with the
token uh the the text right
W but now it becomes phon so this is one
kind of difference right uh and then uh
the in the hmm cases we also actually
using the hard
alignment and in this cases for example
if this this is the two and in this
cases the hard alignment means that the
first kind of the f
is that aligned to the let's say one 125
and the the other one U would be kind of
align to 60 6 to
18 so this is actually uh the what we
have learned as an hard alignment which
we actually using in the hmm cases as
well but I just want to remark two
differences uh compared with the case
that we have explained in the N2 and Sr
and this kind of hm based
alignment so
first uh W uh the position of the O is
changed right and in the end to end
cases o is actually condition
observation but hmm cases all becomes
actually the the are the the the uh
argument part of the probability and
this is actually based on one of the uh
the product rule actually changing kind
of a swap the order of the observation
part and then it becomes actually likely
this actually becomes a generation of
the speech but this approach is one of
the kind of
important the difference with the N2 and
base
approaches and of course there are
another difference right which is the W
and L but this is more like just using
the different unit and so on so most
like most kind of big difference would
be kind of whether or is kind of a
condition or argument and so one but I
will explain about you know how this
kind of difference with kind of derive
the kind
of use the kind of different
formulations and so on but other than
that the problem is the still the most
important problem is still the alignment
part and so on and then given that we
have this kind of
alignment by the way then actually the
problem becomes very simple right for
example first the five frame
corresponding to T and the first the six
to 18 frame corresponding to U so the
problem before we have an alignment
would be that you know observation of
the 1 to 18 uh will be kind of
represented other the conditioned by the
two of the the P uh and then actually
this uh is not easy to uh solve because
it's we need to consider the kind of two
variable in the condition and 18
variable in the the speech side and so
on however it is very uh if you have
this kind of assign alignment and so by
the way if this is if and how we kind of
get alignment I will explain it in the
two to three lectures by the way it
takes very long time to how to kind of
get the alignment and so on but if we
have a alignment it is very natural to
consider that this probability can be
factorized right from the T to o1 to5
and the U to six to the 18 so once again
similar to the kind of a problem of the
what I mentioned in the the the the hard
alignment CTC RN transducer cases once
we have this kind of P based the the the
alignment we can also the factorize and
simplify this the the problem
easily however by the way uh this
actually derivation is not trivial so
from here to here we actually having a
lot of conditional Independence
assumption so it's very natural that
this you know observation 1 to 5
corresponding to two t and 6 to 18 to
corresponding to U right however the
still we are not sure really that you
know this one is affecting this one and
this one affecting to this one right so
mathematically from here to here is
actually not the the equivalent and we
actually having using the lot of the
conditional Independence assumption from
here to here I use a kind of a the the
the compos the sequence and from here to
here I use a kind of a product rule
product rule doesn't change the
difficulty but given the the assignment
we actually reasonably the assume that
this part can be kind of ignored and
then we actually can factorize this the
two uh the to uh the the the the uh
probab ab ilities and so on so always
remember that uh the some kind of the
two the factorize the problem we
actually always have to consider the
conditional Independence assumption
otherwise the problem doesn't become the
the uh the uh the easy and this is a
kind of General case again if we have a
uh the the let's say this you know the T
J minus 1 + one to TJ is a kind of the
onset and offset information of this
kind of pH and then uh again if we know
the kind of a given this kind of a uh
the uh the alignment information we can
actually factorize this the problem but
it's actually using a lot of conditional
Independence assumption to derive this
one okay so uh the this is the the last
the explanation part today so
um I mentioned that the I will use the
kind of a ph and then the making it as
a
um uh alignment problem but actually
this is a very simplified
explanation uh we usually introduce the
two silence silence begin and the
silence end uh because the edge of this
part is most likely silence and it is
wrong to assign silence part to the uh
the phon so we actually usually kind of
introduce this kind of Silence B and
silence e and so on by the way this the
sum of the system are the this the make
a distinction of the silence beginning
and the silence end some of the system
regarding both are the same silence and
so but it depend on the system it
doesn't have a big difference but this
uh
representation may not be
enough it's actually uh the T and the U
can actually be may have a more kind of
changes uh for example if we the
pronunce it who and so on uh before uh
in the kind of beginning of the
pronunciation and the end of the
pronunciation can be more the the the
the less stationary but the middle of
the pronunciation can be very stationary
So based on this kind of assumption in
the the hidden Mar of model cases we
actually
even the uh split the unit to the one
the one two three uh and so on so this
the concept uh is actually quite good to
modeling the uh the speech that used to
be so the uh the problem of the hmm
based the system to the make alignment
is actually little bit more complicated
than the uh the CTC or other cases again
we have a silence
symbol and we also have a T and U but it
can be actually uh the the the
represented as the three types of the uh
F and then that we try to kind of find
the alignment problem once we get the
alignment we can actually uh the model
it uh the other the the a lot of
mathematical uh tools and so on but
again the this kind of a the alignment
is not unique we don't know the answer
we cannot actually have an answer so we
always have to consider this other kind
of a this realization of the alignment
is actually probability this one can be
like for example 30% and this can this
one can be 10% and so on always we
consider this kind of alignment as a
probability and then are solving this
approaches actually for this that the
hidden Mark model is the very important
tools that to do
that okay so this is the kind of the the
summary of today's uh the
uh uh the lecture so first uh the I kind
of try to
uh um provide the information important
information input and output are
different and then uh we need some
alignment and for the soft alignment
case I already I introduced part which
is based on the attention based the
approaches but the majority of the
method is actually hard alignment based
approaches which is used for the CTC R
transmissor and the HM based the
approaches and so on so that's the the
today's uh the lecture